Please welcome back after the Easter break.
I hope you all had some, you know, good time with friends and families.
So we are going to start after the break where we left off.
So if you remember we were covering precise exceptions, we are figuring out the principles how can
we handle precise exceptions in a processor and then today we are going to start from there.
So I think one of you have probably asked this question that how exactly a machine with precise
exception gets to know when the result is available, right.
So we're probably going, we're going to answer that question over here.
So for the course of today's lecture and tomorrow's lecture, I'm going to take the lectures because
Professor Muthlu is travelling for Cool chips Conference school chips.
So I'm a, so that my name is Rahul.
I'm a 25th Safari PhD graduate.
I recently graduated actually.
So currently I'm working at Huawei Research in, yeah, a couple of shops from here.
So previously I have worked at various capacities in Intel labs and an AMD.
And if you have any questions regarding today's lecture or any question in general, if you want to
ask me, that's the best way to reach me out.
So I traditionally walk in micro architecture and memory system design, for example, let's say high
performance, you know, memory storage system design, prefecture cache management, disaggregated
memory systems.
Yeah.
So that that's kind of my area of research interest.
And so I in my PPSDI have focused more on to the data-driven micro architecture.
So what exactly do we mean by this machine learning assisted policies inside the processor to make
better decisions like for example in memory systems in even in this out of order processor, you
know, many types of machineries we can the decision for that we are making, we can think of many of
those decisions can be driven by machine learning methods.
So that's what I have explored during my PSD.
So that's, you know, the the title slide of my PhD thesis.
As you can see that that's the title of the thesis.
If you're interested, that's the the link over there.
So feel free to go, you know, explore this directions and if you are interested in general in any of
the topics that we are covering here, you are getting exposed to, you know, cutting edge per
microprocessor design as well as, you know, many of this topics that you would be seeing over the
course of the lecture if you're interested.
So we are also looking for, you know, people who can join us as full time as well as, you know,
interns.
So definitely reach me out if you guys want to, you know, take a jab from the industry's
perspective, what the problems that we are seeing at this point.
OK, so with that said, so let's let's just jog the memory a bit over.
Did we leave off?
So, so we have like in the three weeks back we have covered some micro architecture fundamentals
before the Easter break.
We have also seen like how, how we designed the pipeline processor design and we you know, we saw
control dependence, data dependence handling, We also and then we ended up in precise exception.
So what sort of state machine that we want to we have designed to enforce the precise exception.
And then I hope you all are in the same page.
That precise exception is needed because of more multiple reasons.
Now one of the reasons is like debugging the program becomes easier.
And so we we would start from there and for the course of today's lecture and tomorrow's lecture, we
would actually try to push the boundary of what we can do more.
So these part of the processor design has been optimised for over multiple decades.
So we are going to give you, you know, step by step understanding of what has been done in the past.
So we would start from out of order execution and we would hopefully end the out of order execution
today.
And then for tomorrow, we would even go beyond the out of order execution to look for opportunities
of, you know, pushing performance even further.
OK, so these are the readings that we are going to do so so Smith and Sohid that paper we have that
that book we have also, you know, mentioned in in the past lecture.
So that's definitely going to be helpful for this course.
And then course of this, you know, lecture and then A2126 for micropulsor.
That's one of the first micropulsor that has this sort of, you know, mechanisms implemented.
So that's definitely a good read if you guys are interested, do this and then tomorrow, hopefully we
are also going to cover branch predictors.
We're going to give give you a flavour of branch predictors.
So that's one of the paper that you can definitely take a look at.
OK, so with that, so, so let's give a quick jog up.
So so this is where we left off last week, right?
So not last week like before the Easter.
So this is what the in order dispatch execution and out of.
Of order completion pipeline with precise exception used to look like right So you have the fetch
decode and you know the reorder buffer inserting stage in the beginning and then after you do this
then you have different execution units which can take variable latencies some of the like for
example integer ad can take one cycle integer multiplication can take even more if you have memory
instructions that can take even more like on the orders of let's say 100 cycles right and then at
the end you.
We have also introduced reorder buffer to maintain the precise exception so that even though
instructions are finishing their execution, let's say somewhat out of order, but then we are not
going to commit them out of order so that we can still buffer the results in the reorder buffer,
then we can commit.
So we have also seen this pipeline stages decode which as I said, like you access a register file,
reorder buffer, you allocate the entry in the reorder buffer, take the instruction if it can
execute and then so dispatch the instruction.
Now keep this in mind that till now what we have discussed that the dispatch of the instruction is
still happening in order.
So meaning that if you have some instructions that cannot be dispatched because of let's say it's
operands are not ready, right?
So one operand or maybe multiple operands are not ready, then anything which comes after that
instruction can also not be dispatched.
So that was the key limitations of the design that we have taken like seen till now.
And then that's what we are going to address in today's lecture.
Then the execution, as I said, like it can, you know, take multiple cycles and instruction can also
complete out of order and then completion.
But then once the instruction finishes its execution, it's not going to, you know, write the result
into the register file, but it's going to hold the result in the reorder buffer.
So that's the, you know, the completion stage here.
And then once we know that OK, this instruction, none of the instructions that happened in the
before this instruction has been caused any exception and this current instruction became the
oldest one, then we know for sure that OK, this instruction is ready to commit.
And then that's the retirement and the commit stage.
We use the name interchangeably retirement and commit.
And then we just simply commit the output of the instructions into the register file itself.
OK, so this this was the, you know, just to jog up of the memory, we have also seen this sort of
data dependence.
So, so the first dependence is the flow dependence is exactly the only true dependence that we care
about because this is the read after write.
So definitely, you know, this instruction cannot be executed before that.
And that's the true data dependence that we that we should care about the any other type of
dependence, like for example, this output dependence.
This is this is like write after write dependence, right?
So this is typically appearing because the number of registers that your program or the compiler is
seeing like the ISA registers that are limited.
Like had you like if you had more registers, you could have actually used a different register.
You just use the register because you don't have enough register at your ISO level.
So that's what the output dependence is.
And similarly that anti anti dependence is basically, you know, it's a write after read.
So this is also another artifact of let's say the less number of registers that you have in the ISA,
but not getting enforced by the programs data dependence, right?
So only data dependence that we truly care about, which is a true dependence that's in the form of
this one.
OK, so we have seen this and we have also seen now how we can handle or how let's say introducing
the reorder buffer can also handle this sort of, you know, the non true dependences, right?
So output and anti dependences how we can handle.
We also showed that you know, if you can, if you remember like we, we renamed this registers into
something called the reorder buffer entry.
And then instead of reading the value of this register from the register file, we actually read it
from the reorder buffer entry itself, right.
So there actually the question came up that OK, how exactly a specific instruction would get to know
that, OK, that register is done, right?
Like, well, how that that mechanism happened.
So that's what we are going to also, you know, shed into light in today's lecture.
OK, so Long story short, this sort of let's say the order buffer that we have introduced that also
gives like that gives us the power to eliminate this sort of anti and output dependences at
runtime.
And it also gives us some sort of an illusion that you in hardware you have more registers that what
your ISA could have provided, right.
So that was the benefit and we are going to tap on that benefit in today's lecture also.
So again like the these are the hardware structure that we introduced last lecture.
So this is this was a register file.
So you if you remember like so register file contains a value valid bit and then the if the valid
bit is set then you know that this value is correct.
If the valid bit is not set that means you know that OK that value you cannot trust.
But what you need to trust you need to look for this tag.
So tag is basically.
Think of it like a pointer, right?
So if you if you like pointer in terms of your, your code that you write.
So instead of reading the value from here, you actually go what the pointer says to this structure
and this structure is going to give you the value, right?
So that's what the reorder buffer is.
And if you remember, reorder buffer also has some sort of, you know, it's a circular queue, right?
So you have the oldest instruction, you have the new youngest instruction, and each entry in the
reorder buffer also has multiple, you know, attributes embedded inside.
So I'm not going to go into, you know, too much detail into this, all of this prior concepts that we
have introduced.
So these are the this is one example that we have also shown in the Pentium 3 processor.
And that's what, you know, our course of today's lecture is going to start.
So as I showed like so this chart and this illustration, I'm going to come back to this, you know,
illustration again.
So what we said that OK, so before going forward, let's let's you know, come to the same
nomenclature.
So dispatch is basically the act of sending an instruction into the functional unit, right?
So renaming the renaming the ROB stalls the false dependence we we can eliminate using the re order
buffer.
But the problem that that we are still facing is that once the instruction gets decoded and you
allocated this into the reorder buffer and the reorder buffer showed that this instruction cannot
be executed at this point.
Why?
Because one or many of your source registers are not ready.
Then what you do, your pipeline actually stalls like you cannot feed any other instruction that is
coming after this to the execution unit, even though they can be executed.
So let let me give you an example.
So I mean, Professor Moodle, you know, keeps on showing this figure pictures.
So that's a long latency instruction that strolls the pipeline.
And then, you know, independent instructions are getting blocked not to go into the execution unit.
So I'm not going to go into too much into detail of these pictures again.
But yeah, so that that's the problem that that we wanted to show.
So, so let me let me give you a concrete example just to, you know, tangibly explain this thing.
So if you look into this, let's say piece of code.
So this piece of code and this piece of code are exactly similar except from the fact that this is a
multiplication instruction and this is a load instruction.
That's the only thing, right?
So what am I showing over here is that this ad is actually dependent on this multiplication.
Why?
Because there is a true dependency, right?
So you are reading R3 which is getting produced by the previous instruction and that's the true
dependence.
Similarly, in this case there is a true dependency over here.
But then any instructions in the blue, if you look into this, all the instructions in the blue, they
are completely independent of this red instruction.
But by virtue of the machine that we already designed, none of these instructions can be can be feed
to those execution unit.
Basically, it cannot be dispatched unless this red instruction gets to dispatch and the red
instruction gets to dispatch only when the mall finishes.
So in this case also the rate instruction only gets to execute only when the load finishes.
So that's the critical part of the problem or the critical problem of the pipeline that we have
designed till now.
So even if you can see that there are independent instructions that could have been executed, but
your current design cannot execute it.
So let's let's try to fix this thing.
So as I said, like what are the similarities?
The similarities is that there is a like a this dependent instruction that is blocking everything
afterwards between these piece of code and that piece of code.
But then the how these two codes are also different.
The difference being is the following that in the left hand side piece of code your R3 is actually
dependent on the multiplication.
Now multiplication is still a deterministic operation like you know by the virtue of your design
that's a multiplication takes 4 cycles or maybe 6 cycles what not.
So that's a deterministic latency, right?
But on the right hand side, the load instruction, it does not have a deterministic latency.
Why?
Because if your load is found in the cache then you can actually service that load in a very fast
rate.
Like you know 3 cycles, 4 cycles.
But then if your if your load misses the cache hierarchy then you don't know like that's a gamble.
Like if it is coming from L2 cache, probably you would see some somewhere around 10 cycles.
If it's coming from LLC, then it would again take some, you know, 1020 cycles more if it is going to
DM that's completely different, you know, point.
So the whole part of the problem is that this dependence, the source instruction of the dependent is
also non deterministic.
You don't know at compile time what exactly is going to happen, what is the latency of this load.
So that how that exactly is important.
So we will, we would come back to this a bit later.
So if you think of it in this way, if you know that OK, there is a deterministic latency dependence,
then you know exactly how.
Many instructions that you should anticipate after this guy to find out that OK, if I put this red
ad, let's say 5 instructions later, I would be fine.
And all of the instructions that you are feeding in between are independent.
Why?
Because you know that OK multiplication has a static latency.
If it is latency 4, then you would try to manage a, you know, gap between 4:00.
If the compiler can manage right with the independent instruction, that can be done in this case.
But it might not be done in this case because at compiler level you have 0 idea what the load
latency is going to be.
Because unless you are actually executing in the runtime, you don't know.
So that's what you know how these two pieces of code are different in some sense that if you tell
the compiler that, OK, I know that there is a dependent instruction coming in.
So let's make, let's make this 2 instructions, the source and the dependent instruction far apart
and feed anything which is independent of these two in between.
Now, if you know what is the latency, you know how many you have to like, what is the distance that
you have to maintain?
But if you don't know the latency, then anything that you are going to feed in it may or may not
work.
So that's the part of the problem.
So I'm, I'm going to come back to this again.
So again, so, so what's the problem?
The problem is essentially that coming from the fact that we are having it in order dispatch, we
call it, you know, you use this terminologies interchangeably, dispatch scheduling or execution.
So the obvious solution is that we go for out of order dispatch, right?
But then the it's not that easy to do.
So let's let's take it, you know, step by step, like how how can we go from Indiana order dispatch
to the out of order dispatch?
The idea is actually pretty simple again, and you have seen this thing before.
We have introduced the concept of data flow execution, right?
So in this case, what we want to do, we want to go back to that paradigm.
So we want to say that, OK, one instruction, we can execute that instruction when all of its source
operands are ready.
So that's the part of the data flow.
So, so that's what I'm writing over here that we want to fire an instruction when all of its inputs
are the source operands are ready and the the data flow actually takes this even more.
But we are not going to, you know, go all the way into the data flow paradigm.
But what we are going to build is essentially a machine that from programmer's perspective it gives
you flow of the von Neumann architecture, which is a traditional, it's a sequential logic, but
internally it's going to behave as a data flow machine.
So you're not exposing the entirety of the data flows, you know a paradigm outside because as a
programmer that's actually very hard to program those machines.
So from programmer's perspective you are still giving an illusion of a Von Neumann machine, but
internally you would execute each instruction.
In a data flow manner.
So that's what I'm going to, you know, motivate in in this lecture, but then before going there.
So this is one way of handling this.
But as I, you know, mentioned before that there are multiple other ways of handling like one thing
that I just made a like a quick trailer that you can also use compiler to detect this sort of data
dependency at compile time and handle this thing.
So that's what I showed over here that if compiler detects that, oh, these two instructions are kind
of, you know, they are producer consumer relationship.
So let's keep the consumer far separated from the producer and feed some independent instructions in
between so that by the time producer consumer gets executed, you would have a guarantee that OK,
producer is finished.
But then that only works if you know that what is the latency of the producer.
If your producer's latency is variable, then compiler has zero idea OK how many independent
instructions that we want to feed.
So that's one problem.
The second problem is you may or may not actually see those many independent instructions.
So compiler's perspective, the life becomes harder.
Hardware becomes much easier if you go for the first principle, but then compiler's life becomes
harder.
OK, so, so this is one way of addressing this problem.
So any other way, can you think of any other way to address this problem?
So let's say I would go back like so this thing, so there is a dependence.
Any other way that you can think of addressing this?
Anyone think a bit differently?
If you, if you're in a computer architecture lecture, anything that you see a problem, just first
ask yourself this question.
Can I predict?
Can I speculate something?
Yes.
OK, so you want to store.
Instruction somewhere like OK, keep it aside, let them or let the other ones go and once that gets
ready and then then fire it up, right.
So that's exactly what we are going to do in out of order.
So out of order we are going to create something called, let's say you know, resting station or like
a reservation station.
So any instruction that you cannot fire at this point, you would just keep it aside, let the others
go as long as they can go.
And then once they get ready, they would also go.
That's that's that's one of the solution, yes.
Anything else?
Yes.
Uh huh.
OK.
OK, so that, that's actually a fascinating thing.
So I'm, I'm I'm going to expand a bit what what you just said for the control flow.
You can actually also do this for the data flow.
So what what I'm going to like extend your solution is that if we can actually, let's say predict
that, OK, what is the output of this R3 is going to be?
Even though R3 is going to take, let's say 4 cycles, I would just simply speculate, OK, maybe R CS
value is going to be 0.
I don't know.
If you predict something, then you know that, OK, this instruction can go on, right?
So because, you know, have some sort of speculative value for R3.
So just keep on executing that.
But then at eventually when if you realise that, oh, I have made a mistake, that prediction was
wrong, then you need to again re execute everything.
So that's exactly what you mentioned it from the control flow side, but this is exactly what can
also happen for the data dependency breaking.
So exactly.
So that's that's what the second solution is for what we call the value prediction.
So value prediction meaning that if you have a producer consumer relationship, just predict what the
producer is going to produce so that your consumer can at least go on, right?
If your speculation is wrong, you go back and then retry.
So now if you can easily imagine, obviously you cannot speculate and keep it going, even your
speculation is wrong.
Why?
Because then that would affect the correctness of the program, right?
So value prediction only works in cases where you can literally predict the value very accurately.
Otherwise the amount of work that you would waste by speculating is going to overpower your
benefits.
So that's why you know value prediction works if you're let's say program is going on in a very
predictable pattern.
But if it is not, then value predictor actually can harm performance.
But value prediction is one of the solution.
Other solution anyone?
Anything.
OK, maybe the other solution is a bit bit tougher for you to guess, but this is one form of, you
know, multi threading, which is called fine grained multi threading.
Fine grained multi threading says that oh, I don't care about the dependencies.
I mean, obviously I do care about dependencies, but I am not going to get bottlenecked by the
dependent instruction.
What I'm going to do is like every cycle I'm just going to execute from different threads.
I'm going to execute 11 instruction from thread one, next cycle from thread 2, next cycle from
thread 3 and go on.
And then again I would come back and go on.
So the hope is that if you have enough threads then if you see that OK one produce an instruction
then at least you can execute the other instruction from other threads before you come back to that
thread again.
So that there is a time gap between this.
So what is exactly happening in fine grade multi threading?
You are not making each single thread fast.
You're making all of them run together.
But then if your single thread performance is not that great, also your whole system's performance
would increase, but the single thread performance may or may not increase.
So that's the upside and the downsides of multithreading, fine grained multithreading.
So the whole part of the question that or, or or the motivation that I wanted to show is that there
are alternative approach for, you know, out of order execution.
But all of those approaches have their own pitfalls.
And that's the reason why out of order execution is so powerful and so dominant in today's, you
know, process design.
Anything that you are probably using your phone, your laptop most likely have some out of order
process.
If not, you know all the course, all those processes have out of order execution.
OK, so that's what the we are going to do.
So so what's the key idea of automatic execution?
It's basically as you mentioned like so if I have some non ready instructions, get out of the way.
Let make the Viper make the highway going for the instructions that are ready to.
Execute right.
So that so this is what I'm writing over here.
So move the non ready instructions out of the way of the independent ones such that the independent
ones can dispatch.
So that's exactly what you mentioned.
So that's what out of what the execution is going to do where exactly we are going to keep them
aside.
It's basically what we call reservation stations.
There are multiple nomenclatures in the literature.
People call it, you know, instruction queue.
People call it reservation station.
But you know, we like the name reservation Station because it's like a highway kind of thing, right?
So if you're not going to use the highway, don't stop in the middle of the highway.
Just set aside and keep the other traffic flowing.
And once you are done, then you can join the highway.
So we're going to do it a bit differently.
So we are going to just do it in a way that, OK, all the instructions would by default would go to
the reservation station and they would come back whenever they're getting ready just to make the
scheduling and all the, you know, the control logic much more regular, OK, so that's the whole
idea.
Now the the The thing is that we are going to monitor the source values of instruction that are
resting in the waiting area because that's what exactly going to know that OK, now I'm ready to
execute.
So once all the source values of an instructions are available, then you know that OK, I can fire
this instruction and they can merge on the highway.
Now they can you know, start getting executed.
OK, so that's merging on the highway is basically what we are calling that instruction would get
dispatched to the functional units which whether it's adder multiplier, load store, whatever.
So it would go over there.
So that is that is happening in the control flow order.
So you would you would fetch the instruction in von Neumann order sequential, but you would execute
them in a data flow order.
So that is the real benefit of out of order processor that you are not exposing this data flow graph
to the programmer because it you are still giving the illusion of sequential execution, but
internally it is actually executing based on data flow.
OK.
So the benefit is obviously that latency tolerance that, you know, if you have independent
instructions in the sequence of instruction stream, then those like independent instruction can
still go on while the other instructions may actually still be waiting on the reservation station.
OK, so this is what the timeline would look like.
So I'm just going to give you like a quick rundown.
So in case of in order dispatch with the precise exception, this is recall like this is what we left
off from the last lecture.
So, and this is the, you know, code sequence that we are going to execute.
So this is Imol ad ad Imol and an ad.
So this ad is dependent on this Imol.
This ad is this red ad is dependent on this ad.
So there is AR3R3, right?
So what's going to happen is that if you in case of Indiana order dispatch.
So once the second instruction, this is the ad would get decoded, then it gets to understand that
OK, I can't execute right now.
Why?
Because I'm dependent on this guy.
So as long as this guy is executing, my previous producer is executing, I can't dispatch.
So what it also does that this the second ad, which is the blue one, which is independent, right?
So that would also get stalled.
So this is the problem that we started with and how the out of order dispatch is going to solve this
thing.
The third one now can also dispatch.
So while the second one is actually waiting on the reservation system side.
So that's the benefit of that that we are going to exploit.
So that eventually if you do this entire, you know, pipeline design, what you can see that OK, this
set of instructions would actually do would have taken 16 cycles if you have in order dispatch, if
you have the out of order dispatch obviously with the correctness guarantee and then there is a lot
of machinery that would go on to make this thing correct.
And that's the whole part of the lecture.
You can actually execute this in 12 cycles and 16 to 12 cycle is like 25%, you know speed up.
So that's quite significant and reality when when you know you, you would see that there are
multiple papers that have quoted that from an aggressive in order pipeline to an out of order, you
would see the speed up somewhere between to 20% to 30% even more.
So that's the power that that we are chasing at this point.
OK, we have question.
Yes, it depends on the register one or one.
So how are these registers having to cost?
Well, the first let us.
Now the second AD writes the value to R3 right?
So oh OK, so probably read it from right to left.
So it multiplies R2 and R1, puts it into R3 and then second one actually reads from RR 1 and R3 and
puts it into R3 again.
Oh, the second ad, second AD yeah.
So the so the second AD can execute with the the with the I mall because when you execute this R1.
With the precise exception, if you recall, like what we do, we do actually for the R1, we say that,
OK, I'm going to produce the R1 not in the actual register file, but I'm going to hold that value
in the reorder buffer entry, right?
So that R1 whenever you're going to write something, you would actually rename that thing to
something else, right?
So it's either going to be reorder buffer entry or it's going to be someone else, right?
So that's that's the benefit that that we would have like if if you like that, that's essentially
going to break this anti dependence or the output dependence that this is not a true dependence as
you mentioned, right.
So that's exactly going to break it that any instruction that comes after this ad is not actually
going to read from the R1 from the register file.
It would actually point it to the reorder buffer entries in the row.
This entry is now responsible for R1 whenever that entry is ready, just take the value from there,
not the register file.
Makes sense.
OK, Any other question?
Yes, in this case I mean, OK, so I'm, I'm showing over here because no, no, no, no, no.
Wait, wait, wait a SEC, wait a second.
Yeah, probably in this case, if you have the in order dispatch, it's not going to cause the problem.
You don't.
You can probably execute without reorder buffer.
But if there is a discrepancy because we're only showing a small piece of code, right?
I mean, there would be something before something later.
So reorder buffer is in general needed to ensure precise exception.
But as you say, like we can use the word drop the reorder buffer, but then you would also drop in
the precise exception losing the debugging capability and everything with that.
OK.
Next question, yes.
No, no, no.
So, So if, OK, if, if I'm, if I understood your question correctly, So if all are all the
instructions waiting for the right back for the dependency to finish, is that what you're saying?
The previous one, right?
So no.
So, so in this case, what would happen?
So you don't actually wait for the right back.
You remember, we, we when we designed the pipeline, we also designed a bypassing path, right?
Like the, the forwarding logic.
So the forwarding logic says that, OK, once my mole is done from this cycle to the next cycle, I
would forward the data.
I don't have to wait for the right back to finish, right?
So I that's the reason why this execution can actually start at this cycle.
If you don't have that forwarding path, then your execution would actually be pushed to this cycle,
right?
So you can you can you can do that timing diagram.
Yes.
OK, that's a good question.
So right back is only going to be doing when your instruction is about to commit for for for this,
you know, for for the course of this, let's say slide.
Think of it in this way.
So when your instruction is not in the speculative path, it's completely anything before the
instruction has also not done, you know, any exceptions and interrupts, we are at the head, then
the right back would happen.
So for the sake of this slide, think of it in this way.
The right back actually updates the architectural state.
Once you're done, there is no going back because that point, if you put a break point, let's say in
in your code that has done for sure before that anything and everything can be discarded also or
they can be delayed to make sure that the right back happens, you know, in in order.
So whatever happens, this W should be going in the ladder execute can finish at before, but the
right well, the West should be going in order.
So that's what the von Neumann machine enforces.
OK, Any other question?
OK, if not so, so let's say what what?
So as I said, like this is a significant performance speed up, but then you also need to make sure
that the machinery is correct so that your instruction is getting executed in the correct manner.
Nobody wants to buy a processor which gives you confidently wrong number.
I mean, that's not LLM for gods sake, right?
So we want to.
Design something that is completely correct.
So what it what does it take to make this process of work?
So this is what we were going to, you know, go go through.
So what are the steps that we need broadly to enable the out of order execution?
So we need 4 steps.
First we need to link the consumer of a value to the producer, right?
So, so there needs to be a connection between the producer instruction and the consumer instruction.
Whichever way it is, we are game.
So we just need to use A tag that says that producer is going to produce this tag X and tag X is
going to be consumed by, you know, consumer Y.
What is that tag X?
It can be really large.
So that's what gives us that renaming capability that, OK, even though I'm from architectural
perspective, I'm actually producing, let's say R11, but internally I'm mapping R11 to tag X.
And that tag namespace can be huge, literally huge.
And that that's what the, you know, width of them or the extent of the parallelism that we can also
exploit from the, you know, processor.
So first, we need to link the consumer of the value to the producer instructions.
Second, we need to buffer the instructions until they're ready to execute.
That's the reservation station that I talked about like somewhere that they would rest before their
operands are ready and they can be fired to execute.
OK.
The third thing that we need instructions need to keep track of readiness of their source values.
Obviously there should be some sort of a wake up logic.
We are going to discuss that, that when the instruction would go get to know that OK, all of my
operands are ready now I can actually file.
So that's the logic that we need.
And the second thing that we need that when all the source of values of an instructions are ready,
then we can disperse the instruction to their appropriate functional unit.
So these are the four broader things that we want to do to enable this.
For the first one, as I said, like for the linking any tag is fine.
What is the namespace of the tag you can think of any broader namespace.
We are going to give an example of what exactly do we mean by tag in in when we are going to do
some, you know calculations or it's a simulations of out of order processor, we need to buffer
where exactly we are going to buffer.
So we are going to introduce a hardware structure called reservation station.
So that's where we are going to put all the instructions.
So think of it in the in the that highway analogy, every, you know, car that wants to go to the
highway, they would first go to that reservation station.
And when they are saying that, OK, now I'm ready to go and merge the traffic to the highway, they
would just simply go to the highway and just start executing, OK.
So that's what the reservation station is.
And then how we are going to enable this in, you know, keep a track of the readiness because
whenever one instruction gets executed and it the execution produces the value, so that can be a
producer, then it would also broadcast the output value to using that tag to all of them.
I'm going to show what exactly does that mean.
And then one instruction or any other instruction can be waken up, waken up, meaning that OK, now
they are ready to execute at any cycle if all of their source operands are ready to, you know,
available at that time.
Now keep this in mind that at any cycle, at any cycle, you can actually have multiple instructions
that are waking up and then say that, Oh my, all of my sources are ready.
Another instruction is also saying all of my sources are ready.
So if you have, let's say multiple instruction at every cycle waking up at same time, then you still
need to have some sort of a scheduling logic.
And then that says that, OK, I'm going to prioritise this guy over the other guy.
So how that prioritisation happens?
So there are multiple, you know, prior works that have let's advocated one over the other.
If you want to think of, let's say in a machine learning way that OK, maybe some sort of fancy
paradise and is going to make the life better, that can actually be useful on in this case also.
So that's, you know, one one of the things that you can also contribute even in this sort of area
that is widely explored.
OK, so that's that's what I say.
Like if the instructions are awake, then you need to select one of which instruction that you want
to fire.
And that selection logic, you can also make it much sophisticated.
I mean, it is already sophisticated nowadays, but OK.
OK, so so Thomasulo's algorithm, so it's named invented by Robert Thomasulo, who is the legendary
designer in an IBM36091 processor.
So this is the first processor that came up without of order execution logic.
So that's why you know, this is one of the most famous algorithm that you would see in computer
architecture named after him, Robert Thomas Low.
So that's one of the way that we can do this.
So if you're interested, definitely take a look at that paper.
The only problem that Thomas Low's algorithm or that incarnation of the machine had is that they
enabled out of order execution, but they did not enforce precise exception.
So that was in a hindsight was a disastrous decision from business perspective, but it was a major
bold step from science progress perspective that this is the first machine that was implemented
using.
Out of photo execution capability, OK.
And then they targeted the functional like sorry, by the floating point units in the beginning
because those are the ones that has actually huge latency for doing floating point divisions,
floating one multiplication and so on.
OK, so, so that's what I said.
Like the major difference is the precise exceptions.
And then there are multiple prior walks that actually like these are the Seminole walks in this
direction, which try to patch that deficiency.
And once you have both of these like you have out of order execution as well as precise exception,
then you have a like a, you know, it's important cocktail to go for the actual product level, mass
deployed processing.
That's what we we we do have in all of our phones.
It enforces out of order execution as well as it also provides you the precise exception.
OK, so that's Interferington flow that that first you know the the one that that uses this paradigm.
OK, So what what exactly we are going to do?
So initially we saw this guy right?
So now we are going to introduce this guy.
So that's the scheduler.
What the scheduler is doing after the decode you are going to put everything in the scheduler.
So that's basically the you know the reservation situation kind of thing.
So all the instruction would go here.
So that part happens in order.
So because you need to give the illusion of, you know, von Neumann machine, right?
So this thing is happening in order.
You put something inside and the entirety of this middle part is happening out of order.
That's the data flow execution.
And then once you're done, you're buffering everything in the reorder buffer.
You're not committing everything all at once because you can't give the illusion to the programmer
also that, OK, it's happening out of order.
So that's also not going to work.
So think of it as like a humpback whale kind of thing.
So you have a head and a tail.
So both of these things are, let's say, happening in proper sequential order, but you have a massive
2 comebacks in the middle.
So one is the scheduler, another one is the reorder buffer.
So everything that happens in between is getting garbled up.
It's pure data flow execution.
And then whatever comes out, obviously I'm not pointing towards that one, but whatever comes out,
that also happens in order.
So goes in order, comes out in order, happens somewhere, gets data flow execution in the middle.
OK, so that's what we are going to look at.
So I'm not going to go too much into detail of, you know, all this previous machines, but these are
really influential and quintessential machines.
So that's one of the, you know, IBMC 1691 in the real, you know, things at that point.
It used to be like a full blown, you know, rooms.
So that's that's another picture of this one.
OK, so before going there, so how exactly we are going to handle this thing, we are going to borrow
many of concepts of the registered renaming itself.
So I'm just going to you know flash through this slide again.
So we have seen that how exactly we do did the registered renaming when we introduce the precise
exception, right.
So your register would now get renamed to a reorder buffer ID.
So it used to be reorder buffer ID.
Now we are going to also introduce the reservation station ID.
So it's basically that's the source where you should get the data.
That's what the idea is.
You have already seen this registered renaming in the previous lectures.
If you're, you know, getting a bit garbled up, so please consult the previous lecture, but we're
essentially going to borrow those concepts from that lecture.
OK, so this is what we, we started with the registered renaming.
So these are the registers that you have available.
We kind of, you know, just reordered things a bit in the illustration.
So you have the tag, you have the value, you have the valid bit, right.
So if the valid bit is set, then you know that the value that you can trust, if the valid bit is not
set, then the tag that's something that you need to keep in track like who exactly is going to give
you the value, right?
So we also, you know, introduce the reorder buffer like this.
So we, you know, we had that re register file, we had the reorder buffer entry.
So that's what we kind of ended up in the last lecture, right?
So we are going to start from here.
So we are going to have this reorder buffer for the sake of our discussion.
For now, we are going to ignore the reorder buffer because reorder buffer is only there for
reordering the results so that you would also commit in order and that's the precise exception.
But we are only going to focus now how exactly you can manage to fire them out of order also.
So that's why I'm just, you know, for the sake of simplicity, we are going to ignore the reorder
buffer.
But at the last part of the lecture, we are going to introduce back it again.
OK, so this is what the Thomas Solis algorithm is.
So I'm just going to go a bit verbose here and I probably need to accelerate.
OK, So what the what the algorithm says if the register reservation station is available before
renaming.
So when you are doing the renaming you you at that stage like after the decode stage you would look
up if the register station, reservation station is available then instruction and the renamed
operands are inserted into the reservation station.
Only rename if the reservation.
Is available, obviously if you don't have parking space, then you can't do anything then your things
would get stalled.
If you have parking space, then get parked and then you can go on.
Yeah.
So that's that's the install part.
And while you are in the reservation station, each instruction is going to watch the common data was
whatever you know for tag of its sources.
When the tag is seen, you would grab the value from the source, keep it in the reservation station.
When both the operands are available, instruction would be ready to dispatch.
Don't worry, I'm going to give you a pictorial example of what exactly this means.
And I'm just, you know, reading through the Volvos part of the algorithm first and then we'll go to
the example.
So once you're all the opponents of an instruction are ready, then you can dispatch the instruction
to the functional unit.
When the instruction is ready and once the instruction gets executed, your execution is done, then
we would, you know the, the, the result that the instruction generated, it would be broadcasted
through the common data bus.
So that's the CDB.
And then register file, reorder buffer, reservation, station entry, everything is kind of listening
to that common data bus.
It would say that, oh, this tag is now generated with this value.
I'm going to just capture that value.
If the tag is matched, I'm going to capture the value.
And then I would consider that, OK, if my instruction is dependent on that tag, now I have the
value.
So if all of my dependence are met, I can actually find the instruction.
OK, so that's that's what the, you know, the very boring way of saying what Thomas and his
instruction is going to do.
And we are going to give you one example of this thing.
So before going to the break, I would probably just, you know, introduce a bit and then we would go
to the break.
I'm running so slow.
I'm not probably an out of order machine at this point.
OK, so, so we are going to take an example of this piece of code and how exactly this would get
executed by out of order processor.
OK, for the sake of this example, consider that your pipeline is let's say you have only four states
fetch, decode, execute and wherever write back execute can be variable.
So if you have addition then that takes four cycle latency.
If you have multiplication that takes six cycle latency.
OK.
And we are going to you know, see how this instruction, let's say all the pipeline designs that you
did first non pipeline processor to a pipeline processor, but in order dispatch to out of order
dispatch, how exactly this this progresses?
OK, so let's let's you know see first part of it and then the out of order, I'm going to show it
after the break.
So if you don't have a pipeline, then what happens?
You have what you have 3 additions to multiplications.
You can do the simple math.
So this is going to take 50 cycles if there is no pipeline whatsoever.
So every instruction there is no overlap.
It's just everything exposed one after the other.
So that's going to take 50 cycles.
You can do it easy math.
Now we can go for let's say in order to dispatch pipeline, but without forwarding like your the
question that you ask like OK, what happens where if you have forwarding without forwarding, right?
So this is what what I'm going to show over here.
So if you have without forwarding, then I would probably go back to this once more.
So you can see that this is a multiplication instruction and this multiplication, this add is
dependent on this model, right?
So what we are going to see, multiplication takes 6 cycles.
If you don't have the forward path, then you need to wait for the ride back to finish and then you
can decode this instruction.
If you do the math that would come out to be 31 cycle, which by itself is benefit or improvement on
top of 50 cycles that you started with, right.
So that's one stage of benefit that you have pipeline processor without any bypass path, then you
can improve it upon further.
It's a pipeline in order to dispatch pipeline processor with forwarding.
So if you do forwarding, then what happens that I'm just going to show one example.
So the second instruction instead of getting, let's say decoded at this place, it can actually
forward the data from the execution of the the once the execution finishes of the previous
instruction.
So then it can start executing over here.
So that if you do the math that already comes down to 25 cycles.
So you started off with 50 with non pipeline processor UN you already see 25 cycles with whatever
that we have covered till the last lecture.
Now what we are going to cover is basically it's going to truncate this down 25 cycles to even for
the 220 cycles, it may not be looking really big because it's 25 to 20.
But if you see it from where you actually started on, even if you see it from here.
So this is like, you know what 20% performance improvement, right?
So from 25 to even 5% less.
So that's what we are going to do.
So previously we used to have this example on, you know hand handwritten thing, but I'm going to
just use the presentation over here.
OK, So I think we can take a break here and let's meet after 10 minutes and.
Sitting down.
Everyone sits down.
OK, so we are going to start where we left off.
I will try to, you know, accelerate as much as possible, but let's see how much I can do.
So we saw this piece of code getting executed by non pipeline processor with 50 cycles.
If you have pipeline processor, but with, you know, no bypassing.
We saw that it it, you know, taken down and then you have, you know, with bypassing, you already
ended up in 25 cycles, right.
So I'm going to show you like how we can do without of order dispatch using 20 cycles.
So that's that's what the, you know, you know, thing is going to be.
So before going there, so let me set the stage before start.
We will start simulating this, you know, small piece of code.
So on the on on the top over here.
So that's the piece of code that we are going to execute.
It's essentially the same that I showed before.
It's just written in a nicer fashion.
And so so each each execution unit.
So we have two execution unit for for example.
So you have the addition unit and the multiplication unit and addition unit takes like 4 cycles.
But consider this thing.
So 4 cycles is also pipeline.
Pipeline meaning that every cycle the addition unit can take 1 instruction.
So internally think of like how we pipeline the processor, we can also pipeline every functional
unit.
So not all the whole part of the AD needs to be done at 4 cycles.
You can let's say you know stage it in four different cycles.
So every cycle it can take 1 instruction.
Similarly for the multiplication unit also it can take 1 instruction every cycle.
OK, so that's like the pipeline execution unit.
And for every execution unit you also have the reservation station.
So that's the reservation station for ADD reservation station for multiplication.
OK, so we start with all the reservation stations are invalid and empty.
So in this case, what exactly each reservation entry is storing.
So you have 4 reservation entry for ADD 4 for the multiplication.
So what each entry is storing.
So each entry has A tag of the entry.
Then whether this entry is valid or not, if that is not valid then which tag it should be looking up
and what is the value?
So this is for operand one or the source one.
And this is also for the source 2.
Similarly you will also have the same thing for the multiplication unit.
So I'm going to, you know, as we go on, this would get clear like how exactly we are going to
populate this thing.
And then we have the register alias tables on the on the, you know, all the registers are actually
also starting with the valid.
So these these are the valid bits.
All of them are one.
That means all of these values can be trusted.
OK, so this is the stage of what we want to start with.
OK, so now let's let's let's go 1 by 1.
So cycle zero, we fetch the first instruction.
Definitely nothing else happens at this point.
So that's not sorry, cycle one.
This gets fetched now cycle 2, so the first one gets into decode stage.
So now we want to decode this.
So what happens?
So first instruction is a multiplication R1R2 goes to R3.
So what we do?
So we say that OK, First things first, do we have any reservation station entry for multiplication?
The answer is yes.
They all of the things are free, right?
So we know that OK, there is a space OK, then we want to say that OK, what are my source registers?
That's the first line of, you know, understanding whether I can execute this guy or not.
So my first first register is R1.
What is R1R1 is valid.
So that means I can trust the value.
So what did I do?
I simply copy that value saying that OK, my first register is R1.
So that's the valid bit that I copied.
That's the value that I can trust since it is valid means that I am I can trust this guy.
OK, Similarly, I have this another operant which is R2R2.
What is R2R2 is also valid and we would just copy it over there that OK, R2 is valid and R2's value
is 2.
OK, Now the third part of the, the, the, the operations that we are going to do.
So now we are going to write R3.
So R3 would be produced by me.
So what we are going to do, we say that OK, now whoever comes after me should actually read R3 from
me.
So how would I do this?
I will actually say that OK, now R3 is invalid and then you keep A tag of X.
So that means X is the one who is going to give you the result.
So you have seen this thing for the precise exception using reorder buffer, right?
So you used to have the reorder buffer entries number over there.
So now I'm actually putting the.
Tag over there.
So that's the tag that you got OK, so at this point what what exactly does that say?
It says that OK, you this instruction has two operands.
Both the operands are valid.
It's generating some data which is, you know, X and you put the X over here because now it's
generating R3R3 is invalid.
So anyone who wants to read R3 now would see that OK, this is not valid.
That means the value you cannot trust this value you actually need to pull for this tag, OK?
Is this clear?
If that's the case, then another thing that you you can also see that both of its operands are ready
because it's both of them are valid.
So that means from the next cycle onwards, you can actually start this instruction.
Makes sense.
So that's the logic that we we already come up with that OK, If both of them are valid.
So that's a wake up logic.
Then you can start this instruction.
OK.
And the second time at this cycle also the second instruction gets fetched, which is the, you know,
the nature of the pipeline.
Now let's go to the third cycle.
So what happens?
So your first instruction start executing life is good.
The second instruction now gets decoded.
What is the second instruction?
It's the add instruction.
You do the same thing.
So I mean that that's what we are sure showing over here.
The both the operands are ready.
So you can wake up and you can start the instruction and that would go to the multiplication unit.
It's going to take 6 cycles.
So 6 cycles, meaning it's going to finish in cycle 8.
And then there is it's going to be too many operations going on in that cycle.
So we'll come back to that.
OK, So it gets, you know, so it's starting the execution at at this cycle.
Now the second instruction would now start getting decoded.
So what what do we do?
We do the same thing that we did for before.
So what we're what we're going to do?
So we would first read, OK, who is my first operand?
My first operand is R3.
Now guess what?
R3 is not ready anymore.
R3 you would actually get OK, 0X.
So you blindly copy the 0X0X, meaning that zero basically tells you that this instruction is not
ready.
At least one operand is not ready.
What is the second operand?
Second operand is R4.
Yeah, R4 is ready.
So it is going to be 1/4.
So tag is don't care.
And then what is the destination?
The destination is R5.
So now you just rename this R5 to say that OK, whoever comes after me now would read this entry.
It would say that OK, R5 is invalid and redirect them to entry A, which is the reservation station
entry A.
That's what the pointer is.
So it is basically you're creating a pointer inside your hardware, right?
So you do some changes and now this guy is now going to be represented like responsible for doing
the value.
So anything who comes after this ad now needs to read R5 from this guy, not from the anywhere else.
Makes sense.
OK, so that's that's what happens.
And then, you know, you also execute like face the next instruction.
But you can easily see that OK, so this instruction is not ready to execute at this point because at
least one of the operands is not ready.
So at next cycle, you cannot fire this instruction.
That's the, you know, the data dependency that we met.
Yes.
Oh, the till is like don't care.
Like if, if, if the value, if the valid bit is 1, then we don't care about the tag.
So it's like, you know, don't care.
I don't care.
What's the value over there?
Sorry, yes, so, so we so valid bit is 1, meaning so the~ basically I'm using it like a don't care,
you know, operant.
So I mean don't care, meaning that since this is valid, then value is already ready.
I don't care about this guy, but if it is invalid, then I do care about what is exactly written over
here, which is X.
So that's what the~ is.
OK, are we clear till this point?
OK, so now let's go to the fourth cycle.
So fourth cycle, first one keeps executing, so that's fine.
The second one, unfortunately we can't execute because we already saw that there is one invalid guy.
OK, so that's life is good.
The third one now starts getting decoded.
So what happens?
We do the same thing.
R2R2 is already ready.
So that's one and two.
And then we also have the second operand which is R6R6 is also ready.
Now guess what?
So both of these operands are ready.
So that means you know for sure that this can be executed at this point.
So that's the out of order dispatch that you are enabling.
So if you had the machine which is in order dispatch, you couldn't have actually exposed this
execution.
Now you can actually expose this execution.
Make sense?
So let's finish this instruction.
So now this instruction is also going to write R7.
So what we are going to do, we are going to just simply write this guy.
We say that OK, now anything that comes after this instruction now needs to read this R7 to AS0B,
meaning that this value is not ready and whoever needs this value should now consult this entry.
That's the whole idea.
Makes sense.
Clear.
OK, so now let's you know.
The next one and then let's go to the cycle 5.
So what the cycle 5 is doing so the first multiplication is going on.
The second addition can can still go on the third one now can go why?
Because the third one is essentially this ad.
So which ad is this one?
So this can actually start executing.
So that's again, that's the power of out of order dispatch, right?
So you have both the opponents to be ready.
So you just Simply put both the operands over here.
So six goes here, two goes here and the tag also goes here.
So each this this functional unit after four cycle is going to broadcast the both of these things
that all B is done.
So that would be appearing over here.
And the result of 6 + 2 eight would be appearing over here after 4 cycles.
So that's going to be cycle number 38.
OK, does it make sense all with me?
OK, so now we decode the 4th 1, so the 4th and is R8 to R9 we do the same thing and I'm I'm not
going to you know, do do it the animations by itself.
So so this was the state.
So as you can see that when we decode the first one, so R8R8 is going to be valid, R9R9 is also
going to be valid so that we would end up in this state.
So this is valid.
This is valid and R10 is going to get written.
So R10 would be pointing TO0C, correct?
Everything is fine.
OK, so now you can easily see that this instruction is also getting ready, also ready to get
executed.
So that's another instruction that you discovered which can be executed out of order, right?
So while this guy is waiting, you can still execute this to add.
That's another discovery, right?
So sixth cycle, your multiplication is still going on.
Your second first addition cannot move.
Your second addition can move.
Your third addition can also move, which is this this C, right?
And now the, you know, the 5th instruction gets decoded.
So what is the fifth instruction?
5th instruction again, like R7R10, you can do the same thing.
R7 is 0B.
So I'm, I'm allocating the second entry.
I'm not going, you know too much into detail, but you can see that R7 has this first operand to be 0
B, second operand to be 0 C, which is R10R10 is 0C.
So you put it at 0C over there.
And what am I writing?
I'm writing R11.
So R11 becomes zero.
And why?
Why?
Because This is why this is the reason why you know if anything comes after this instruction or
needs to read this kind make sense.
Are we clear?
OK, I can see nods yes question.
So when result it's inside the reservation station, right?
Yes.
This is waiting.
This is chilling.
Both of them are chilling.
Yes in the pipeline order or no so, so B got fired first.
So B started execution.
B is the second ad which is this 1.
So it started execution then C got fired.
So it's just like a pipeline one by one.
Just wondering when we do it in pipeline then we can actually have just one summation like
complement other.
Oh yes, yes, if you if you have another adder, you can just you know, start both of them together
also.
But with one adder, it's also possible because addition itself is taking 4 cycles, but it internally
is pipeline so it can take one in new instruction every cycle.
So it's also going like internally step by step.
Makes sense.
Are we clear?
Yes, there's just a section of the actual reservation station, but we also have to store the
destination register and the OP code.
And so starting over here, no.
So anything, anything that is getting this, like all the destination registers would also get
renamed over here.
Just execute what we find in the reservation station.
So we need to know where to store well, how the value is getting stored.
Like once the value is ready, I'm coming back.
Hold on any other question.
OK, so let's go to the the 4th one like the seventh cycle now so seventh cycle is this so execution
of the multiplication going on ad cannot move on second ad is going on the third ad is going on the
1st, the second multiplication which is this guy you can easily see that OK now this multiplication
cannot go on because both of its offering are not ready.
So definitely you can't go on.
So you need to, you know, chill till your.
All the operands are ready, OK, and then you get you decode the 5th, the last instruction.
Now this instruction is a bit complicated, so follow through.
OK, So what this instruction is doing, it's actually reading R5 and writing R5 both together.
Look at this.
OK, So what we are actually doing, so we first go one by one, first look up the source, populate
this, then our change the destination.
That's the algorithm.
So you look up the source.
What is R5R5IS0A?
So you do 0A.
What is the other source which is R11R11IS0YR11IS0Y.
Then what you are writing, you are writing R5.
You overwrite R5 again.
So now R5 is getting overwritten.
So previously it used to be 0 A.
Now you would overwrite and then it would make it 0 D So what exactly happened?
So what exactly happened is the following.
So R5 got produced here and R5 got rewritten here.
So anything that came between these two saw an entry OF0A over here.
So any instruction that came between these two would know if I need to access R5, I would go to
entry A.
But the moment this ad came in, it read from A, but then it written to itself.
So in the architectural register space, you have still have the R5 and R5.
But in your execution stage, what we did, we said that OK, now R5 since R5 is now getting generated
by this entry, now anything that comes after this ad now needs to get R5 from D.
So that's what basically happened that OK, now R5 got again renamed to A tag D So what exactly does
mean that if any instruction comes after this and wants to ask for R5, it would actually get the
value from B, not value from A.
That also makes ensures that OK, you are getting the correct value in the program order, not in the
incorrect value.
A is gone.
The the the, the A is whoever has a over here, right?
And I'm coming, I'm coming.
So, so when this instruction would be generating the value, we would actually broadcast that tag
over here.
So I'm coming.
I'm coming.
So what happens to the A and where did it go?
Uh huh.
Say that again.
The A is gone.
So what?
What happens?
So, OK, so that's a good question.
So, so look at this instruction itself, right?
So this instruction still needs A, and now a is gone from here.
So how exactly this would ever get resolved and then make this valid bit to one?
That's a genuine question, right?
Because a is not even here.
So what this entry means that it this entry means that I'm listening for tag a.
So now when whoever generous and I'm coming to that later.
So when you would generate some answer from this execution unit, it would actually broadcast the
output as well as broadcast the tag.
Here we have saved it here, the a is not there.
But here we have actually saved the a.
So we are going to match the logic here, here, here, here and here.
So anywhere we would find a, we would just replace with the value.
So a is gone from here.
So that means we are not going to replace here, but we would replace here.
I'm going to come.
I'm going to show you like what exactly is happening.
So since tag is gone from here, so think of tag meaning like it's it's a pointer, right?
So you don't have the pointer.
So that means you are not going to update this guy.
Why?
Because that from this guy's perspective that R5 is renamed, but someone needs the R5 over here.
So you're not only going to broadcast the tag to this registered areas table, you're also going to
broadcast tag to this reservation station.
This reservation station both opens.
And I'm the hopefully the, you know, the next few slides is going to make make that clear so that
that is the part of the cost of this machinery.
So you need to literally broadcast everywhere?
Yes.
Uh huh.
Yes, yes, we are going to come back to that.
So hopefully I'm I'm going to, you know, give you that output that OK, at the end of the day, R5 is
what R5 is literally this entry.
This entry should actually compute the correct value and you can you can cross verify what it's
going to do.
OK, OK, so now, so all the six instructions have been decoded.
They have all already put into the reservation station.
So I hope that you are your, you know, good over here.
Do we have any question, any confusion at this point?
OK, if not, so let's let's go.
What happens in RA?
I mean, cycle 8.
Now cycle 8 starts making lots of more, you know, communications.
So First things first, multiplication finished.
So multiplication.
No, sorry, actually.
So multiplication is going to be finished at this cycle.
So that means it's finished.
So even 6 cycles are done, right?
So what what actually happened?
So multiplication, when it's done.
So it's going to multiply 1 into two, it's going to create the value 2.
And it's also going to take this tag X.
It's also going to put the tag X over here.
Now I'm going to broadcast this tag the entire place.
So I'm going to broadcast the tag first to the register alias table.
Check whoever has this thing then I'm going to broadcast it for the source one of reservation
station one, source 2 of reservation station one, source one of reservation station 2 and source 2
of reservation station 2.
It literally gets broadcasted everywhere.
Makes sense.
So once you broadcast this tag X, you saw that OK, there are two entries which are seeing the match
one entries R3 and another entry is this guy.
So which which means that now both of them are not transient anymore.
I have the data or what exactly that value is.
What is the value?
Now you broadcast the value, OK that becomes true.
This becomes true and then your valid becomes 1.
So that means now that value is ready.
Now at this point if somebody reads from this, it knows that OK, the value is correct.
Is this understandable?
So you're literally whenever you're completing A execution, you're not only broadcasting the value
of the execution, but who generates it.
And that tag is getting broadcasted not only to the register area stable, but also to this all the
source operands of all the reservation stations.
So that's a huge broadcasting wire.
And these things actually cost, you know, the area increase power, increase everything.
So that's the reason why this is so power hungry structure in out of auto processes.
Is this clear?
Any question?
Yes, used for optimization that it will be broadcasted to everyone.
So it does not need to think of who really needs it or not.
Yes, that's a naive way of implementing.
But we can also optimize this as you say, like you know, you we have actually done a lot of
research, not we I mean past decades and in multiple decades we have done a lot of research that to
optimize that.
OK, how can this broadcast can be, you know, narrowed down?
Yes.
OK, so now let's let's see what what else is happening on this case.
So add one, sorry, this second add is also done, right?
So what is the second add?
Second, add actually stays here.
So it started in cycle 5 and now it ended in cycle 8.
So that's what we are seeing over here.
So two and six gets added.
So that's your value 8 and this is the tag because this entry is getting, you know, done.
So that's the tag of B.
What you do, you do the same thing broadcast the tag over here.
So that's the tag match and then broadcast the tag in the source one.
Broadcast the tag in the source two.
There is no no one that is consuming this.
Can someone consume this?
Yes.
So this is another match and then broadcast the tag to this one.
There is no one that is consuming.
So now you know that OK, anywhere that you're going to find this tag B, let's just update that tag B
with the value 8.
So I'm going to update this eight.
I would put eight over there.
Make it the make the valid bit to one.
Put eight over here, make the valid bit to 1 make sense.
So now you can see that OK, once your value gets generated, it starts populating that structure or
as well as it also start, you know, modifying this structure.
So the reservation system also is seeing that OK, things are actually getting, you know, completed.
Now at any point of time, any cycle, we would also check whether all of my source operands are done.
Then I can also find that instruction.
So, so that's when that's what happens.
So now, now the second, the third ad is still going on.
So we don't have anything over there.
And you know this multiplication, which is this one, this still has this thing left, so it can't
start.
The last ad, this has still this, so we can't start.
So do we.
Have any, any new instruction which is ready to execute at this point?
Probably not.
So now let's go to the cycle #9 so this is done.
The first guy is done.
Now first guy is committing, meaning that it, it, it, its effect to the final architectural
checkpoint is done.
So then that's not going back.
We are not going back to from that part at all.
Now the second guy, So what, what happened?
So once, OK, I actually forgot this One South.
So the first ad since your multiplication got done, so the first ad is this guy.
So this guy's one of the operand which was the the first opponent.
This operand was 0 before.
So if I go back, so before this, this operands at cycle 8, this operand was 0.
But you, since you broadcasted this, now both of these operands are actually ready, so it can
actually start from cycle #9 So that's what we are going to show over here.
So this is cycle 8.
So cycle 9 that gets done, and then cycle 9, this can start.
So this guy was actually chilling in Reservation Station.
Now since both of its operands are ready, now it can start its execution.
So that's how we are also maintaining the data flow.
Is that clear?
OK, so now what we do?
So OK, so now, so the second ad is also done.
The the third ad now gets done now, right.
So at this cycle, so the third ad is done.
So who is the third ad?
Third ad is essentially here.
So what it was doing, it was adding eight into 8:00 and 9:00.
So that becomes 17.
It's done.
So that means I'm I'm broadcasting C.
So I'm broadcasted C and 17 to all of them.
So I am not animating everything so but if you if you go back, so it used to be C over here and C
was here.
So I am updating both this and this to be 17.
So now this is not invalid anymore.
That is not invalid anymore.
Makes sense.
Now you can also see that this multiplication had two source operands.
One of them were not ready but that got ready at this cycle.
So now this multiplication can get fired like it can start its execution makes sense.
So from the next cycle what what we are going to see is that this multiplication is reservation
system Y is ready to execute.
So we are going to start the cycle execution in the next cycle.
So that's what we are in the cycle 10 is.
So first instruction is done, second instruction is in the same getting executed.
You know, the that ad is also done.
You can start this multiplication.
So that multiplication is getting started for what is what.
This AD cannot still go on because this is the last ad.
None of the operands are ready at this point, so it still needs to hold back.
OK, so I'm not, I'm not, you know, animating this one because this is just a mundane execution
cycle.
So cycle #11, you still execute.
Now let's go to cycle #12.
So what happens?
The cycle #12 this ad is finishing.
So what is the this ad?
This is the first ad.
So first ad, meaning that this is this ad.
So you used to be like this before you start the cycle 12.
So what did you do?
So you added two with four.
So that means it's coming 6 over here, and then this is a over here.
So you would broadcast A through the entire thing, broadcast A on this tag, broadcast A on this tag,
this tag, and this tag.
Who has A?
Nobody has A over there.
So this is what you ask, right?
So nobody has A over here.
So I'm not updating A anywhere here.
But now who has A?
A is here actually.
So even though A is gone from this table, A is still here.
So when this ad gets finished and then this is getting finished at this cycle, you're actually
broadcasting A and six.
You would match A over here.
No one is.
No one has A this guy had a so we we started with this.
So now that means that this is ready.
So you actually make it make it valid and that would take the value 6.
Make sense?
Is this clear when I am going a bit too far, but I think can understand if just let me know if it's
not going inside.
I did not show the broadcast.
I mean, that's animation, but I can, I mean, This is why I said like if you, if you start at the
beginning of let's say cycle 12.
So think of what is happening.
So at cycle 12, this this ad is finishing.
So let me let me animate this to you like for you in mind.
So this ad is finishing.
So what is this ad?
This is the first ad.
So first ad goes to our first reservation station.
That's how we we did it.
So what is the first reservation station?
He's doing 4.
+2 sorry, 2 + 4, that becomes 6.
And who is generating it?
A?
So a comes here, then a would get broadcasted over here, over here, over here, over here, over here.
Make sense?
So a is vanished from here because you have rewritten.
So nobody is going to capture that value at this point, but somebody has A here, so that is actually
going to capture the value.
So that's how a a got resolved over here.
So if that tag is alive anywhere in the either in the reservation station, Oregon, in the registered
area stable, it would take the value.
Is that clear?
OK, so now, so that's why you know the multiplication is going on South.
That's that.
And then we end up in the OK, so this multiplication, so this is right back.
That's also finished.
And then then this is E 5, which is the multiplication.
Multiplication is still going on.
And then at this cycle 15, this multiplication is finishing, right?
So let's let's go back what it used to be.
So at cycle 15, this multiplication is finishing.
What is this multiplication?
This is the second model, meaning we are actually in this entry.
So what it does it's multiplying 8 with 17 so 8 into 17 that coming to be 136.
So 136 is getting calculated by this entry.
So why?
And 1:36 get broadcasted who has this thing?
So let's go back.
This guy has why this guy has why there is no other why.
So this entry would be updated.
This entry would be updated with 136 and 136.
So now guess what this all of the opponents are done.
So that means this can fire after, you know, 4 cycles from now on, this would complete and then this
would be done.
It would say that OK, D is done.
D is computing 142.
You broadcast, you put 142.
That's the final output.
So you start with all valid, you end with all valid.
And what is the output of the value?
Because R5 is the final one that is getting renamed, right?
So you would expect the final value to of this program to be here, and that's the final value of
this program to be here.
Now the tax is just, I mean, in this example, yes, in this example, yes, obviously.
I mean, if you if you have a long program, then then this keeps on going at this point.
Yeah, at this point, the tags are 11.
What does this mean?
It means that every value that you have in the registered alias table is correct.
So if somebody wants to read the data from them, just read it there.
You are not dependent on someone.
That's it and that's what it is happening.
So you are you are done with all the instructions, you are done with all the instructions.
Is that clear?
OK, so if this is this case, then you know, let's just you know, accelerate a bit since we are kind
kind of running out of time also.
But So what, what do we, So what are the other design choices that we need to ensure to, to have
this sort of, you know, design?
So what is it in the hardware to perform this tag broadcast and value capture?
Like this is what I showed.
Like the tag is getting broadcasted everywhere and whoever the tag matches, then it would just
simply capture the value, right?
So that's, that's the common data bus that we showed.
So obviously we need to make the value valid.
We wake up an instruction that's, you know, another form of circuitry that we need to need.
So these are essentially new wires comparators and logic.
So that would be going over there.
So that's adds complexity.
Now the other question is that does the tag need to be the same idea of the reservation station
entry?
The answer is no.
Like as long as you have any consistent nomenclature to map the producer with the consumer, I don't
care what is the tag for this example, we have A tag of each entry, but you can literally put
anything over there as long as you have this, you know, producer consumer relationship obey.
So what can potentially become the critical part?
So this tag broadcast to value capture to instruction wake up.
So this is the broadcast wake up logic.
So that actually becomes the critical part of this out of order machine.
So that is why, you know, there has been numerous research over multiple decades of out of order
processor design that tries to, you know, do this this critical part to be as short as possible.
So like when we want to wake up this instruction, when can we can anticipate that, OK, this
instruction is going to get finished and so on and so forth.
OK, so, so that's what it is.
So now another funky or another, you know, good experience for you could be that if you start with,
if I, if I give you any snapshot and then this is I'm not going to cover in this lecture because
I'm, I'm really running out of time.
But if you if I give you the snapshot of any cycle for this, in this case, let's say the snapshot of
seven cycle, you can actually backtrack and then see that OK, where exactly this data?
Dependency graph is coming like which instruction is dependent on which ones?
You can build this data dependency graph and then come back with this sort of instruction in a
sequence.
And that's fascinating that you can do this.
So I would I would not go too much into detail of this, you know, reconstruction, but definitely
check out the the previous, let's say incarnation of this lectures video of this, you know,
lecture.
So we professor Muthu actually reconstructs this graph by hand.
So that might be useful also.
OK, so I'm I'm not yeah, unfortunately I'm not going to go into too much of detail.
But what exactly you go, go we are going to see is that basically you would see this getting
created.
Yes.
So what we just saw was Thomasulo's algorithm.
Yes, Thomasulo happening in real life.
Now if I, if I tell.
So what I'm saying now is that if I give you any snapshot of Tomasulo's in action like this, like
OK, this is the snapshot of the processor at cycle 7, you can actually backtrack and then create
the dependency graph.
So that's what this would look like and you can backtrack this thing.
And that's not Tomasulo's algorithm.
This is just for our understanding sake that OK, whether you understand the out of order execution
correctly or not, like which one has what dependence and then who produces that dependence and who
consumes that dependence.
That's it.
Yeah yes.
So I'm I'm coming back to to that one S right now.
What till what?
Whatever I have shown is basically you know for without precise exception.
So we don't have well like we have not included reorder buffer in this you know design.
But if you want to have precise exception then we need to also add the reorder buffer.
The logic is not that complex.
So it's I'm just going to go briefly into that design also, but essentially, if you have the reorder
buffer, then you would also have you know, the the one that you said that OK, checkpoint something.
And then if you go to, let's say handling interrupt or handling, let's say exception, you go there
and then come back and restore the checkpoint.
So we can do that with with the precise exception support.
Yes, OK, anything this might be actually useful.
So just you know, go and take a look at previous lectures videos so that you can also, you know, we
showed the top down, you can also go bottoms up like if I give you the snapshot of that state, you
can also build this graph.
And then that's fascinating.
I think I mean you can you can take a look at that.
OK.
So some other questions that we are we are not answering at this point is that when the reservation
station increase de allocated.
So ideally when your operation is done like your AD or multiplication is done, then you can simply
de allocate the entry.
But there are some providers that let's say if it is executing on the wrong part like meaning
speculatively executing and so on and so forth.
So that bit complicates the process.
But we are not going to go too much into detail of of those answers.
But this is just a question that you can ponder about like.
There are multiple other sorts of, you know, complexities that are involved like should the
reservation station need to be dedicated to each functional unit or it should be global?
Like these are just design questions, right?
So there are good sides and the bad sides of both the designs.
If you have centralized, if you have distributed, you know, if you have the centralized, then it's
becoming bigger, then you need a big boss to go through.
But if you make it distributed, then you can actually have like shorter wires to broadcast.
So that also tones down like that also reduces your power consumption.
This is your, you know, energy consumption and everything, right?
So those are multiple, you know, questions that we can ask.
Should the reservation station and the ROB both stores value and or there would be, you know,
centralised things.
So this and I'm going to, you know, go up a bit much into detail.
So, so, yeah, so and then the other thing that that we wanted to briefly touch up on before going
forward is what you ask, like if you have, let's say, precise exception support on this system.
So what happened?
So, so we started with this one.
So this is like add addition of four cycles, multiplication of 6 cycles.
And then we ended up using 20 cycles as I, you know, promised.
But then if you go for, let's say precise, like with precise exception support, then you would add
another, let's say, stage, which is the reorder buffer update.
But essentially it goes on the same way, but from the hardware structure side, like when the
hardware structure side, we can actually optimise a bit.
So that's what I'm, I'm going to, you know, show a briefly touch upon over here.
So the idea well out of the execution with precise instruction is that OK, you use a reorder buffer
just to simply simply reorder the instruction before committing them to the architectural States
and instruction.
They're going to update the RAT when it completes the execution.
So.
So there would be like 2.
Two different register files now, so one would be we would call the front end register file.
Another one we would call the, you know, architectural or the back end register file.
So the front end register file which we already showed that register file is what we showed it's
going to be called front end initiative file, meaning that you would update whenever you see the
broadcast, just update it over there.
You don't know whether this broadcast is happening or this instruction is getting executed
speculatively, non speculatively fine, you just update.
But then you would have another register file on this back end, which we call the back end register
file or the architectural register file, which is the one when the instruction finally commits.
So once you commit that gets into architectural checkpoint.
So that is let's say the view that you are giving to the programmer that this is happening correctly
1 by 1 SI am going to go into, you know bit more detail.
So we started with this.
So this is the register alias file, this is the reservation station with for the AD reservation
station with the multiplication, this is what we explained, right?
For the without precise exception, if we have precise exception, what we want to do, we added
another reorder buffer which is there to reorder the, you know, execution completions, right?
So that's what the reorder buffer is.
And then we also have another register file.
So this front end register file from the previous one, this architecturally this is exactly same you
would update the way that I just described, but this is a different 1 S This one is what we are
calling the back end of the architectural register file.
It means that it's never going to have anything invalid or in transit.
It's always going to have some value, which is I know that these values have been committed.
So this is only going to contain the value that your program has already completed and then
checkpointed over there.
So at at the end of the, you know, the commit stage of 1 instruction, that's the only place when
you're going to update this architecture register file.
Now if you have any, let's say the the beauty of this you know, design is that if you see any
exception getting raised somewhere in between this, you know, this would have some of those zero
values, the tags and all of these things would be flying over here at any point of time.
Let's say some instruction raise some exception, right?
So what would you do?
You know that OK, none of this you can trust go back to this one.
Just copy this value to this and restart the machine.
That's what you are going to do.
So you have one copy.
Once you know that OK, this reorder 1 instruction becomes the oldest one and you can commit this guy
that is only going to commit, commit this one.
So think of it this way, like you are doing so many stuffs, but then something is also getting
checkpointed at the end like, and that is the final checkpoint.
Like you, you know that that is the correct thing and you would never come back from that.
Only when if your program starts making something interrupt all, let's say exceptions and that
that's what the idea over here is.
And then yeah, if you add the reservation station on the same picture.
So this is the full blown, first time, full blown picture of what exactly is kind of similar to what
is going on inside your phone.
So you have your buffer, you have front end register file, you have architect register file, you
have reservation, you have reservation for all the, you know, functional units.
You can obviously optimise this even even further.
So I'm I'm just going to show you again, I like showing that camel.
So one thing that you can you can see just further optimization.
And then I'm going to, you know, close this thing.
So you can see that there are multiple, you know, phase where your value is getting replicated,
right?
So there is a value over here, there is a value in the reorder buffer.
There is a value in the front end register file.
There is also value in the, you know, architecture register file.
Now, if you ask yourself the question, what is the value?
Like what is the size of a value?
If you have a 64 bit machine, your size of a value is 64 bits, right?
Now what you can do like your programming mind would say that OK, instead of storing the value, just
store the pointer, right?
If your size of the pointer is smaller than your size of the value, then you would save.
So what would you do?
The obvious choice is that, OK, keep the entirety of the value in one file.
That's what we call the physical register file.
Now this physical register file, you are just simply going, everybody is going to just point to
this, right?
So your front end register is now instead of storing the value, it's just going to store the
pointers to this guy.
Similarly, your reorder buffer instead of storing the entire value is going to store the pointer.
Similarly, your architectural list of file instead of storing the value is going to store the
pointer.
The what is the benefit?
The benefit that I'm trying to, you know, convince this to you is that if you're register, you know,
with the 64 bit.
This the number of physical registers, let's say you have 1000 registers, maybe 2000 registers, how
many bits you need for representing 2000 registers you need only 12 bits, right?
So 12 bits is much lesser than storing the entire 64 bits.
So that's what we are doing over here that you just simply store the pointers and this is somewhat
that you actually are going to see in the real systems.
So this is the version of the pipelines that you're going to see in the real system.
OK, So yeah, I think we can, we would close this over here.
Maybe I have some few slides left on this, this, you know, lecture.
Maybe we can just complete this tomorrow and then tomorrow we would start from this out of order and
then we would see that OK, how we can push it even further with super skill and stuff.
OK, so have a good day.